Finding Aid for Martin Mayman papers, 1945-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Martin Mayman papers
1945-1997
Mayman, Martin.
027 Aa 2
Director of psychological training at the Menninger Foundation (1951-1966); professor of psychology at the University of Michigan (1967-1999); associate director (1967-1973), later co-director (1974-1981) of the Psychological Clinic at the University of Michigan. The collection consists of correspondence, drafts of writings, published articles, research notes, lecture outlines and transcripts, audio recordings of lectures, committee minutes, and psychodiagnostic scales and tests.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the children of Martin Mayman (Donor no. 8949 ) and came to the library in 2000.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Martin Mayman was born April 2, 1924 in New York. He received his B.S. in mathematics and psychology from City College of New York in 1943, his M.S. in psychology from New York University in 1947 and his Ph.D. in psychology from the University of Kansas in 1953.
From 1951 to 1966, Mayman was director of psychological training at the Menninger Foundation in Topeka, Kansas, where he founded and directed the post-doctoral training program in clinical psychology and pioneered several well-known psychodiagnostic procedures, such as the Early Memories Test.
Mayman completed psychoanalytic training at the Topeka Institute for Psychoanalysis. He came to the University of Michigan as a visiting professor in 1966 and became professor of psychology in 1967. Mayman retired in 1997 from active faculty status. On March 20, 1998, the Regents of the University of Michigan granted Mayman emeritus status.
In addition to being a professor of psychology at the University of Michigan, Mayman was a clinical psychologist at the Psychological Clinic, Institute of Human Adjustment. Additionally, Mayman served as the associate director of the Psychological Clinic from 1967 to 1973 and as its co-director from 1974 to 1981. The Psychological Clinic was founded in the 1950s under a special Rackham Endowment.
Mayman's early research focused on personality assessment, psychological testing and projective techniques. He later became interested in the subject of shame and its role in development and psychopathology.
Mayman was a prolific author, writing on topics such as Early Memories, the Rorschach, Psychopathology, and Clinical Psychology. He authored or co-authored 28 articles on psychological testing, many of which have become classics in the field. Mayman was also the recipient of many awards from professional organizations, receiving, among others, the Distinguished Contributions Award from the Society for Personality Assessment, the Distinguished Service to the Profession of Psychoanalysis Award from the American Psychological Association, Division 39, and the Distinguished Contribution to Psychology Award from City College of New York.
He died March 18, 1999.
The Martin Mayman collection has been arranged into five series: Correspondence, Writings, Drafts and Notes, Seminars/Courses, Subject Files, Menninger Clinic, and UM Psychological Clinic.
Subjects:
Mayman, Martin.; Early memories.; Psychology.; Psychological tests.; Menninger Clinic.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Psychological Clinic.
Contributors:
Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990.; Rapaport, David.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence series contains communications between Mayman and other academics and professionals in the field of psychology. The correspondence primarily discusses Mayman's research and writings. Correspondence regarding the internal activities of the Menninger Clinic and the UM Psychological Clinic has not been included in this series. The series has been arranged chronologically.
  - 1953-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1997 (Box 1)
- Writings, Drafts and Notes
  Writings, Drafts and Notes series documents Mayman's prolific career as a published author and co-author. The series has been arranged chronologically to help illustrate the evolution of Mayman's writing and research interests. Many articles contain multiple dates. This usually indicates that multiple drafts and re-writes have been included in the folder. The files usually contain multiple edited versions of the particular writing rather than the published version. Co-authors have not been indicated in the finding aid.
  - "Intelligence test and concept formation: a review of the literature,", 1945 (Box 1)
  - "The development and functions of the ego,", 1947 (Box 1)
  - "Diagnostic testing in convulsive disorders,", 1947 (Box 1)
  - "Reliability in analyzing Thematic Apperception Test stories,", 1947 (Box 1)
  - "Research in diagnostic testing,", 1949 (Box 1)
  - "Review of the literature of the Thematic Apperception Test,", 1949 (Box 1)
  - "The interpretation of the Wechsler-Bellevue Intelligence Scale in per-personality appraisal,", 1951 (Box 1)
  - "Personality facts in Osteoarthritis,", 1951 (Box 1)
  - "The characteristic psychological disturbance in some cases of brain damage with mild deficit,", 1952; 1954; 1960 (Box 1)
  - "A study of the sense of self,", 1953 (Box 1)
    (Mayman's Ph.D. thesis)
  - "Developments in psychology on the outpatient section during the past year,", 1955 (Box 1)
  - "The diagnosis of mental health,", 1955 (Box 1)
  - "A narcissistic character,", 1955 (Box 1)
  - "On the concept of psychological health,", 1955 (Box 1)
  - "A tentative guide for quantifying the state and degree of disintegration ('illness') within the three presently used zones of 'mild,' 'moderate,' and 'severe,'", 1955 (Box 1)
  - "Episodic Dyscontrol: a third order of stress adaptation,", 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Rating scale for the blatancy of oral aggressive content,", 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Critical review of Freud's Beyond the Pleasure Principle,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Earliest memories: their use as a diagnostic device,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Image association test,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Insight Test,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "On the professional identity of the clinical psychologist,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "The psychological test diagnosis of ego-identity factors,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "A re-examination of Freud's logic and conclusion in Beyond the Pleasure Principle,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Some notes on the 1957 written examinations for ABEPP," 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Teaching psychiatric residents to use a brief battery of psychological tests,", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Comments on self-concept research,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Epigenetic relationship paradigms,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Early memories outline,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Guide to a qualitative analysis of responses on the Wechsler-Bellevue,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "A psychoanalytic theory of the self,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Role perception and the patterning of interpersonal relationships,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "Toward a psychoanalytic reformulation of self theory,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "The unitary concept of mental illness,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "The use of early memories as a diagnostic procedure in work with patients and relatives,", 1958 (Box 1)
  - "A clinical inquiry into individual forms and qualities of self-experience as reflected in a person's early memories,", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Clinical Psychology,", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Early memories and abandoned ego states,", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Definition of normality,", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Discussion of Gardner Murphy's Paper: Some broad human drives and how they become attached to some broad 'human objects,'", 1959 (Box 1)
  - Paper read at Law-Science Institute, 1959 (Box 1)
  - "A study of episodic dyscontrol eventuating in homicide,", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Style, focus, language and content of an ideal psychological test report,", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "The characteristic psychological disturbance in some cases of brain damage with mild deficit,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Digest of the characteristic psychological disturbance in some cases of brain damage with mild deficit,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Early memories as expressions of relationship paradigms,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Ego strength and the potential for recovery from mental illness,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Helen Durham Sargent,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Murder without apparent motive: a study in personality organization,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Perceptual, ideational, and interpersonal implications of the Rorschach Movement Response,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "The prescription of treatment,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Reconciliation of ego identity data with the initial form B assessment of patient variables,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "The self-preservative tendencies of the ego: a re-examination of Freud's Beyond the Pleasure Principle,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "The WAIS as a clinical diagnostic tool: a review,", 1960 (Box 1)
  - "Developmental relationship paradigms,", 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Toward a Science of Clinical Inference,", 1961 (Box 1)
  - "Early memories and abandoned ego states,", 1962 (Box 1)
  - "A dimension of personality organization,", 1963 (Box 1)
  - "Ego identity proposal,", 1963 (Box 1)
  - "Psychoanalytic study of the self-organization with psychological tests,", 1963 (Box 1)
  - "The analysis of children's early memories,", 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Current critical issues in clinical training,", 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Discussion of paper by Dr. Mark Kenzer,", 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Normal and pathological narcissism,", 1964 (Box 1)
  - Paper on phenomenology for Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - "Postdoctoral professional training: how and why?,", 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Survey of first level inference drawn from psychological tests,", 1964 (Box 1)
  - "The individual in psychoanalytical theory: a psychoanalytical theory of the self,", 1965 (Box 2)
  - "The psychic apparatus,", 1965 (Box 2)
  - "Psychoanalytic perspectives on self-theory,", 1965 (Box 2)
  - "Psychopathological changes in response to disintegrative threats,", 1965 (Box 2)
  - "University teaching of the Rorschach: some suggestions from a teaching clinician,", 1965 (Box 2)
  - "The psychotherapy process and its relation to ego-closeness--ego-distance,", 1966 (Box 2)
  - "Diagnostic and treatment implications of ego-closeness--ego-distance: autokinesis as a diagnostic instrument,", 1967 (Box 2)
  - "Object-representation and object-relationships in Rorschach responses,", 1967 (Box 2)
  - "Autokinesis and character style: a clinical-experimental study,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Blue book: general propositions implicit in the clinical application of psychological tests,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Early memories and character structure,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "General propositions implicit in the clinical application of psychological tests,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Psychoanalytic perspectives on self-theory,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Research project on the psychological and psychopathological implications of the autokinetic illusion,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Studies on the ego-structural implications of early memories,", 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Levels of object representation and object relationships in early memories,", 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Object representations and object relationships in early memories,", 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Quality of object relationships in early memories,", 1971; 1973 (Box 2)
  - "Psychoanalysis as a science,", 1974 (Box 2)
  - "The shame experience, the shame dynamic, and shame personalities in psychotherapy,", 1974-1982 (Box 2)
  - "Self--other relationship representations in early memories,", 1975; 1977 (Box 2)
  - "Self-representations, object representations and relationship representations in early memories,", 1975 (Box 2)
  - "Psychoanalytic theory in retrospect and prospect,", 1976 (Box 2)
  - "A re-examination of diagnostic testing,", 1976 (Box 2)
  - "Developmental relationship paradigms: illustrative memories,", 1977 (Box 2)
  - "Oral aggression as an organizing theme in perceptual style and character structure,", 1978 (Box 2)
  - "Psychoanalytic psychotherapy,", 1979 (Box 2)
  - "Psychiatry and psychology: conflict and resolution,", 1979 (Box 2)
  - "Transaction of the Topeka Psychoanalytic Society,", 1979 (Box 2)
  - "The treatment of primitive mental states,", 1979 (Box 2)
  - "Clinically meaningful aspects of the analysis of a set of early recollections,", 1980 (Box 2)
  - "Features of the infantile character structure (as seen in both men and women),", 1980 (Box 2)
  - "The phallic bridge to femininity in young adult women,", 1981 (Box 2)
  - "Narcissism, object, and self: a psychosexual theory of normal and pathological narcissism,", 1981 (Box 2)
  - "Multiple personality: a re-analysis of the case literature,", 1982 (Box 2)
  - "A re-analysis of the literature on multiple personality,", 1982 (Box 2)
  - "Guidelines for a program to support research on the range of psychodynamic therapies from time-limited to psychoanalysis,", 1983 (Box 2)
  - "Notes for a paradigm for outcome research in dynamic psychotherapy and psychoanalysis,", 1983 (Box 2)
  - "Quality of object representations scale,", 1984 (Box 2)
  - "Clinical theory and object relations theory,", 1985 (Box 2)
  - "Psychosexual self theory,", 1985 (Box 2)
  - "A study of gender-linked determinants of the transference psychoanalytic psychotherapy,", 1985 (Box 2)
  - "Object relationship paradigms in early memories,", 1986 (Box 2)
  - "A research study of determinants of transference and counter transference in psychoanalysis psychotherapy,", 1986 (Box 2)
  - "Shame, guilt & Disgust,", 1992 (Box 2)
  - "A brilliant lecture (psychoanalytic paradigms),", undated (Box 2)
  - "Characterological determinants in style of psychotherapy,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Experiential and expressive attributes of affects,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Instructions for administering supplementary tests for ego identity,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Neurotic Disorders,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Phallic Bridge,", undated (Box 2)
    (Carol Barber)
  - "Phallic-urethral conflicts and their effect on the course of psychotherapy,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Quality of life odyssey,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Reality contact, defense effectiveness and psychopathology in Rorschach from level scores,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Studies in interpersonal relationship,", undated (Box 2)
  - "Twenty five years of clinical psychology training at the Menninger foundation,", undated (Box 2)
  - "The use of early memories as a diagnostic procedure in case work with patients and relatives,", undated (Box 2)
  - Women in Life, Love and Work Symposium, undated (Box 2)
- Seminars/Courses
  Seminars/Courses series includes teaching material from Mayman's time as a clinical instructor and psychology professor at the Menninger Foundation and the University of Michigan. The course material related to Menninger Foundation has been arranged chronologically and is reflective of Mayman's early research interests in personality assessment, psychodiagnostic testing, and Rorschach psychology. The seminars and courses taught by Mayman at the University of Michigan have been arranged alphabetically by class name. The series also contains transcripts from seminars conducted by Mayman at the York Wood Center and lecture outlines and drafts from various symposiums and conferences attended by Mayman. The series consists primarily of lecture outlines and transcripts, syllabi, audiocassette recordings of lectures, reading lists, and course handouts and exams.
  - Curriculum Vita Materials, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Menninger Clinic
    - Classical Psychiatric Syndromes Course, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Introduction to Psychological Testing, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Theories of Personality Course, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - Psychiatric Treatment Course, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Mayman Seminar, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Training Program, Reading List, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Psychotherapy Seminar, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Inference Seminar, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Rorschach Seminar, 1956-1958; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Basic Concepts Seminar, 1957-1963; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Clinical Use of Dream Interpretation Course, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Perversions and Character Disorders Seminar, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Seminar on Psychoses, H.G. van der Waals, 1958; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - TAT Seminar, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Current Developments in Psychoanalysis, 1959; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Deviant Schools Seminar, 1959; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Ego Psychology Seminar
      - 1959-1960, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - 1961, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1962 (Box 3)
    - Complementary Reading Seminar on Psychology, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Experimental Foundations, 1960-1962 (Box 3)
    - Research Seminar, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Narcissism Lecture, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Rorschach Workshop, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Seminar on research in psychoanalysis, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Clinical Inference Seminar, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Test Report Seminar, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Conferences and Symposiums, 1950s-1980s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan
    - Affect Seminar, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Course Descriptions, undated (Box 3)
    - Curriculum Review, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Lecture Outlines from Department of Psychology, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Teaching Materials, 1985; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Psych. 555, Notebook of Linda Rosenzweig, undated (Box 4)
    - Psych. 671, Clinical Psychology
      - Course Materials, 1976-1986; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Course Syllabus and Lecture Outlines, 1974; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Lecture Transcripts
        - Ego Boundaries, 1976 (Box 4)
        - Multiple Personalities, 1976 (Box 4)
        - Object Relations, 1976 (Box 4)
        - Psychopathology: Borderline and Narcissistic, 1976 (Box 4)
        - Rosen, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Outcomes and Course Notes, 1974 (Box 4)
      - Reading Lists, 1974; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Psych. 672, Clinical Testing (Box 4)
    - Psych. 673-674, Psychological Testing, 1968-1973 (Box 4)
    - Psych. 771, Advanced Psychological Training, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Psych. 874, Adult Psychotherapy, 1982-1984 (Box 4)
      (includes 24 cassette tapes of recorded lectures)
    - Psych. 978, Developmental Ego Psychology, 1970-1982 (Box 4)
    - Psychoanalytic and Ego Psychology, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
    - Psychopathology Lab, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Student Evaluations, 1966-1985; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Workload Correspondence and Forms
      - 1966-1968 (Box 5)
      - 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - York Wood Center Sessions
    - 1978, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1979, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
- Subject Files
  Subject Files series reflects Mayman's many research interests from personality assessment to self and object representation in early memories to Rorschach psychology. This series is helpful when compared with the Writings, Drafts and Notes series because it contains the research material used to help formulate many of Mayman's published arguments and conclusions. The Subject Files have been arranged alphabetically and are made up of assessment forms, testing scales, lecture transcripts, and research notes. Some of the files contain papers with a number written in the corner. These numbers correspondence to the Filing System Index created by Mayman in 1990-1991, which is also included in the Subject Files. However, it should be noted that the Filing System is not very consistent and is incomplete.
  - Abandoned Ego States, undated (Box 5)
  - Affect Theory, 1963; 1970; 1975 (Box 5)
  - Affect Words/Affect Modes, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Affects, 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Aggression, undated (Box 5)
  - Brain Damage, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Case Material, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Clinical Inference Q-Sort Study, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Clinical Theory, 1975; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Color Rationale, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Content Categories, undated (Box 5)
  - Early Ego States, Self and Object Representation, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Early Memories, 1984-1986; 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Early Memories Scales, undated (Box 5)
  - Early Memories Surveys, undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Ego Boundaries, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Ego Identity, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Ego States/Pleasure States, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Embedded Figures Test, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Filing System Index, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Formal Speech Patterns and Impulses, undated (Box 6)
  - Inference Process (Dream Interpretation and Rationale), 1973 (Box 6)
  - Interview Phallic-Style Scale, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Psychological Tests, undated (Box 6)
  - Multiple Personalities, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Narcissism, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Narcissism and Libido Therapy, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Object Relations, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Object-Representation Scale for Dreams, undated (Box 6)
  - Oral Aggression, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - Parallel Process, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Parkinson's Feeling States Study, undated (Box 6)
  - Pleasure States, undated (Box 6)
  - Psychosexual Stages Chart, 1948 (Box 6)
  - Psychotherapy, 1978; 1980; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Quality of Life, 1973; 1985; 1990 (Box 6)
  - Rorschach, 1950s-1980s; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Rorschach Movement Response, 1959; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Sentence Completion Test, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Sequence Analysis, undated (Box 6)
    (includes 2 cassette tapes of recorded lectures)
  - Severity of Pathology Rating Scale, undated (Box 6)
  - Sex Differences in Psychosexual Theory, undated (Box 6)
  - Shame, undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Short Term Analytic Therapy, undated (Box 6)
  - Stimulus Barrier, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Therapy Supervision, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Uses of Affect used in a Histrionic Patient, 1978 (Box 6)
- Menninger Clinic
  Menninger Clinic series documents the research and administrative activities of the Menninger Clinic. Materials related to the administrative activities of the Clinic include correspondence, committee minutes, and background information on the history and functioning of the Menninger Clinic and Foundation. The majority of the papers in the series are related to research conducted by Mayman during his tenure with the Menninger Clinic. The materials related to the research done at the Menninger Clinic consist primarily of assessment forms, testing scales, correspondence, lab reports and findings.
  - Autokinesis Phenomenon, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Case Study, Special Test Battery, 1960; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Children Coping Project, 1960-1963 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Early Memories, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
    - General, 1966 (Box 7)
    - Menninger, Karl, 1949-1955; 1965; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - On Martin Mayman's writings, 1950s (Box 7)
    - On The Vital Balance, 1960-1962; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Rapaport, David, 1953-1961 (Box 7)
    - Wallerstein, Robert S., 1954 (Box 7)
  - Current developments in psychoanalysis, Reading lists, 1961-1963 (Box 7)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Diagnostic Testing, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Discussion of Dr. Kahn's Paper, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Early Memories and Image Association Tests, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Early Memories Conference, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Education Committee, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Empathy, 1949 (Box 7)
  - Experimental Contributions to Psychoanalytic Ego Psychology, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Karl Menninger's Writings, Notes and Outlines, 1951-1956; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - MMPI Scale, undated (Box 7)
  - Menninger Committee, 1950 (Box 7)
  - Menninger Foundation History, 1954-1986 (Box 7)
  - Menninger Research, 1967 (Box 7)
  - The Menninger School of Psychiatry booklet, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Morning Notes of Adelbert Ames, Jr.,", 1947 (Box 7)
  - Nosology, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Patient Cases, 1945 (Box 7)
  - Post-doctoral psychology training program, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Preliminary Report Concerning Body Image Changes associated with Personality Reorganization, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Psychoanalytic Research, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Psychological Test Reports, 1956-1964; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - "Psychology at the Menninger Foundation,", 1954 (Box 7)